Inventory of the John Marshall Papers 1771-1959
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
John Marshall Papers, 1771-1959.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 M34
434 items.
Original letters and copies of letters from other repositories, chiefly 1788-1835, of John Marshall's correspondence with his wife, Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, and other family members.
Marshall Family,; John Marshall,; Mary Willis Ambler Marshall,; James Monroe,; Joseph Story.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1 item, 1/11/1935.
Purchased: 99 items, 12/31/1935.
Gift: 3 items, 7/7/1937.
Gift: 2 items, 4/16/1940..
Gift: 11 items, 6/5/1957.
Gift: 4 items, 10/27/1957.
Gift: 1 item, 10/31/1957.
Gift: 14 items, 12/1/1957.
Gift: 4 items, 12/15/1957.
3 items, 1/01/1958.
Gift: 12 items, 1/15/1958.
Gift: 4 items, 3/3/1958.
Purchased: 13 items, 5/17/1958.
Purchased: 4 items, 8/6/1958.
Gift: 1 item, 10/6/1958.
Gift: 1 item, 5/23/1959.
Gift: 1 item, 6/01/1959.
1 item, 6/04/1959.
Gift: 3 items, 9/9/1960.
Gift: 1 item, 7/8/1961.
Gift: 1 item, 1/31/1962.
Gift: 2 items, 4/4/1962.
Gift: 1 item, 4/23/1962.
Purchased: 3 items, 11/01/1967.
Purchased: 1 item, 10/01/1968.
Purchased: 1 item, 3/01/1970.
Purchased: 1 item, 5/01/1970.
Acc. No. 83-46; Gift: 1 item, 11/01/1972.
Acc. No. 77-34; Deposit: 1 item, 11/01/1977.
Acc. No. 78-44; Purchased: 1 item, 11/14/1978.
Acc. No. 79-23; Gift: 1 item, 10/01/1979.
Acc. No. 82-23; Gift: 1 item, 5/01/1983.
Acc. No. 86-2; Purchased: 9 items, 12/01/1985.
Acc. No. 86-30; Purchased: 1 item, 6/30/1986.
Acc. No. 87-11; Gift: 1 item, 2/11/1987.
Alternative Form
Some manuscript volumes located at the end of the collection are also available in microform in the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. [Reels M-104, M-105(a-c), and M-106]
Biographical/Historical Information
John Marshall (1755-1835) was born near Germantown, Prince William (currently Fauquier) County, Virginia on 24 September 1755 to parents Thomas Marshall and Mary Randolph Keith. From 1775-1781, Marshall served in the Continental Army and fought in the Revolutionary War. During the spring and summer of 1780, Marshall attended classes at the College of William and Mary and received his license to practice law. After the war, he moved to Richmond, Virginia and began his practice. Marshall married Mary Willis Ambler in 1783. The couple had ten children, six of whom survived to adulthood. He was elected as a delegate to the Virginia House of Delegates in 1780 and 1782-1788. Later, he was appointed by President John Adams to a special commission to France from 1797-1798. The commission, which brought about the famous XYZ affair, failed to settle existing differences between France and the U.S. From 1799-1800, Marshall served as a Federalist representative in the 6th United States Congress. He did not serve out his term however, as he was appointed by Adams to serve as U.S. Secretary of State from 1800-1801. Later, Marshall received yet another appointment from Adams this time to the bench as the fourth chief justice of the Supreme Court. He was confirmed by the Senate on 27 January 1801 and served until his death on 6 July 1835. In addition to hearing 1,215 cases and authoring 514 opinions, Marshall also wrote, The Life of George Washington, a book in 5 volumes. Marshall was buried in New Burying Ground, Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Original letters and copies of letters from other repositories, chiefly 1788-1835, of John Marshall's correspondence with his wife, Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, other family members, James Monroe, Joseph Story, Bushrod Washington, and others. The correspondence reflects Marshall's wide range in interests including law, Virginia and U. S. politics, international affairs, agriculture and social events.
Also included are letters by family members and descendants; a charcoal sketch and copies of visual representations of John Marshall; and places and events associated with him.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 4 series. Series 1 contains correspondence and papers of John Marshall, family members and other individuals; Series 2 contains printed material, poems and charts; Series 3 contains prints, engravings, and artifacts; and Series 4 contains manuscript volumes.
Arrangement
This collection is primarily arranged chronologically by date.
Additional Related, Separated and Bibliographic Material
Bibliography
Johnson, Herbert A., Charles T. Cullen, Nancy G. Harris, Charles F. Hobson, and others eds. The Papers of John Marshall. 10 vols. to date. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1974-. Call Number: E302 .M365 v.1 - v.10
Mason, Frances Norton. My Dearest Polly; Letters of Chief Justice John Marshall to His Wife, With Their Background, Political and Domestic, 1779-1831.Richmond: Garrett & Massie, 1961. Call Number: E302.6 .M4 M33
Oliver, Andrew The Portraits of John Marshall.Charlottesville: Institute of Early American History and Culture, University Press of Virginia, 1977. Call Number: E302.6 .M4 O44
Rhodes, Irwin S. The Papers of John Marshall, A Descriptive Calendar. 2 vols. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, [1969]. Call Number: KF213 .M3 R5 V.1 - V.2
Related Material
The majority of the copies, comprising approximately 50% of this collection, are from the Marshall House in Richmond, Virginia; the Library of Congress; or the Massachusetts Historical Society, but other depositories are also represented. For information concerning the location of orginials please see the components listing below.
See also John Marshall Faculty/Alumni File, University Archives, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Separated Materials
Books owned by John Marshall have been removed from this collection. For a more detailed location of these books please see the Lion Catalog as well as the Association Collection in the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Newspapers have been transferred from this collection. See the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Marshall family.
Persons:
Marshall, John, 1755-1835.; Marshall, Mary Willis Ambler, 1766-1831.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831.; Story, Joseph, 1779-1845.; Washington, Bushrod, 1762-1829.
Subjects:
Marshall, John, 1755-1835--Portraits, caricatures, etc,; Lawyers--United States--Correspondence.; Statesmen-- United States--Correspondence.; Judges--United States--Correspondence.; Marriage--United States--History--18th century.; Marriage--United States--History--19th century.
Geographical Names:
Richmond (Va.)--Social life and customs.
Components List
  Series 1: Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, Family Members and Other Individuals
- Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, Family Members and Other Individuals, 1771-1916, n.d. (Box 1-5)
  - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1771-1835, n.d., 269 items. (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1771-1789., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:1-2)
      - Notice from [John Marshall] reminding commanding officers of militia companies, that men whose public arms and accoutrements do not pass inspection at musters should be fined not more than two dollars, [1775-1779?]., 1 page. AL. (Box-folder 1:1)
      - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia], to [James Monroe], n.p. 12 December 1783., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
        Has delivered his [Monroe's] letters to Gen[era]l [George Rogers] Clark and [John?] Banks; discusses proceedings of the Virginia Assembly; R[ichard] H[enry] Lee's services to the Assembly are lost forever and Colo. Harry [Henry "Light Horse Harry"] Lee will probably take his place; mentions bills defining citizenship introduced by [John] Taylor and Colo. [George] Nicholas; tells of [Joseph?] Jones bill and discusses Patrick] Henry's style of oratory; relates the House being split upon the issue of exclusion of the Statute Staple men; discusses military warrants for land and his [Marshall's] father, who set out for the western country on November 5.
        Including Tcy of ALS. 2 pages.
        Originals
        Original is located in the Draper Collection,
        State Historical Society of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, Annapolis, [Maryland], 3 January 1784., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
        Blesses George Washington who resigned his commission of 23 December 1783; will put his [Monroe's] letter to Majr. [John] Crittenden into the hands of Genl. [George Rogers] Clarke, who will be in the western country in February, and who will pay close attention to his [Monroe's] military warrant; mentions that the Speaker [John Tyler] has left Richmond; laments the passage of the bill excluding Virginian delegates to Congress from serving in the Virginian legislature; "Fear of the power of Congress I have ever considered as chimerical;" Colo. [John Francis] Mercer informed him of the passage in the Continental Congress of the resolution accepting Virginia's cession of the northwest territory.
        Including Tcy of ALS. 3 pages.
        Original is located in the Monroe Papers,
        Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
      - John Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, Annapolis, [Maryland], 7 February [17]84., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
        Has enclosed a bill of exchange for the one hundred dollars due him [Monroe] as a Delegate to Congress, four dollars having been expended on his land warrant now in the hands of the Surveyor.
        Including Tcy of ALS. 1 page.
        Original is located in the
        James Monroe Memorial Library, Fredericksburg, Virginia.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, Annapolis, [Maryland], 24 February [17]84., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
        Claims he is unable to send money because inclement weather has hindered state tax collection; [Samuel] Ege and Monroe's former landlady, Mrs. Shera, are clamoring to be paid; mentions the impending marriage of "Little" [John] Stewart and "Kitty Hair" [Catherine Hare]; gossips about "artificial heat" of the courtships of Mr. Dunn and "your old acquaintance" Miss Shera, and of "Tabby" [Tabitha] Eppes who "has grown quite fat & buxom, her charms...renovated," and her unsuccessful suitors: [Edward] Carrington, [?] Young, [?] Selden, [Matthew] Wright, and Foster Webb, [Jr.]; mentions other friends and state officials including [Thomas] Lomax, William] Nelson, [Jr.], [Beverley] Randolph, and [William] Short.
        New York Public Library, New York City, New York.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [James Monroe, Annapolis, Maryland], 15 May [17]84., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
        Colo. [William] Grayson is not here, but [Wilson Cary] Nicholas is; a quorum was reached on Wednesday, [May 12] and committees are being appointed; [Patrick] Henry arrived yesterday and is eager to have postponement of the tax collection; the Speaker [John Tyler] was chosen without a contest; tell Colo. [John Francis] Mercer that there lies £100 in the Treasury for him; he [John Marshall] will tell his [John Francis Mercer's] brother [James Mercer] in Fredericksburg the same; Major [John] Crittenden is again elected for Fayette County; asks him [Monroe] to deliver letters for him to Doctor [Arthur] Lee.
        Photostat,
        Monroe Papers, Library of Congress, Washingon D.C.
        Location of original is unknown.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to William B[ranch] Giles, 22 September 1786., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
        Reports he delivered his [William Branch Giles's] letter to Major [Charles] Magill while in Winchester, [Virginia] in August; discusses gaming act and several points concerning the case of his [William Branch Giles's] client, Mr. Bell; Brother James [Markham Marshall] has arrived from Kentucky and will remain in town through October.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, Trenton, [New Jersey], 2 December 1784., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
        Congratulates him on his return from Montreal and the Northwest; he too wishes that the British debts resolutions had not been passed, because it tends to weaken the federal bands and provides a pretext for the British to retain possession of the forts on the lakes; [Joseph Jones] has introduced a bill to provide for seven annual payments for repayment to begin in April 1786; only bill that has been passed was one granting [James] Rumsey a 10 year monopoly to develop the machine in a steamboat; discusses rejected bills, including one encouraging intermarriage with the Indians; General Assessment and circuit court bills will probably be thrown out, even with the influence of [Patrick] Henry; his [Monroe's] letter recommending Colo. [John Francis] Mercer did not arrive in time to appoint him to a position; [Joseph] James has replaced [William] Short, and [Spencer] Roane and [Miles] Selden, [Jr.] have replaced [Meriwether] Smith and Colo. [William] Christian; [Edward?] Carrington was very disappointed in losing by one vote when Colo. Jack Nicholas walked out on the last ballot; he [John Marshall] attempted too to promote Monroe's friend's interest, Wilson Nicholas, who is about to marry Miss [Margaret] Smith of Baltimore; his [Marshall's] father is willing to help him [Monroe] in regards to his [Monroe's] western lands, but his [John Marshall's] cousin Humphr[e]y Marshall would be better able to; discusses relative merits of selling or keeping his [Monroe's] western lands.
        Monroe Papers, Library of Congress, Washington D.C.
      - [John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], to Governeur Morris, [Richmond, Virginia?], [11 June 1788]., 3 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Invitation to dinner; on verso is poem Extempore at the Convention in Virginia, written by Morris, satirizing the slowness of the proceedings of the Virginia convention called to ratify the U.S. Constitution.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to George Chapman, Summer Hill near Alexandria, [Virginia], 23 July [17]88., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Sends client a second subpoena as the first was never returned, concerning a suit in Chancery Court which involved title to land in Fauquier County, Virginia; asks that any depositions or affidavits be forwarded to him.
      - Petition of J[ohn] Marshall acting on behalf of Robert Morris requesting that the High Court of Chancery of the Commonwealth of Virginia subpoena William Alexander and Company, compelling them to make a full accounting of their dealings while employed as tobacco agents in Virginia for Morris, [ca. July 1788]., 10 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [George Washington], n.p., 5 September 1788., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        In response to a letter of Washington's, he [John Marshall] discusses the legalities of caveats and land patents.
        Henry E. Huntington Library, San Marino, California.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to John Dandridge, New Kent [County, Virginia], 25 April 1789., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Discusses general English legal history of intestacy, and Virginia's laws concerning priority of payment of a decedent's debts by an executor.
      - Indenture conveying Philip and Caroline Turpin's Richmond lot number 786 to John Marshall, 7 July 1789., 2 pages. Pst of ADS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Original is located in the Collection of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, on deposit at the
        Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Virginia.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Thomas Walker, Albemarle, [Virginia], 9 July 1789., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Asks for his [Thomas Walker's] account rendered to [John] Syme for other materials which will help him [John Marshall] to argue his [Thomas Walker's] court case.
        Original is located in the Page Walker Manuscripts,
        University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia.
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1790-1799., 39 items. (Box-folder 1:2-6)
      - Wilson Cary Nicholas, [Albemarle County, Virginia], to John Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], 5 December 1791., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Gives Col. [Reuben] Lindsey [sic] [Lindsay] an order upon him [John Marshall] for twelve pounds.
        Original is located in the Nicholas Papers,
      - Ja[me]s Innes, Duval's to John Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], 28 April 1792., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Discusses his [John Marshall's] financial obligations to him, including £20 for a chariot; asks him to pay the governor [Henry Lee] for a hogshead of wine for him; mentions he is setting out immediately for Williamsburg.
        Including Tcy ALS. 1 page.
        Including Pst of ALS. 1 page.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Francis Walker, Albemarle, [Virginia], 23 February [17]93., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Advises him [Francis Walker] to take testimony showing the value of his [Francis Walker's] lands which formerly belonged to Mr. [Nicholas] Meriwether in preparation of his case; discusses his [Francis Walker's] other case against [William] Cabell.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Charles Lee, Alexandria, [Virginia], 28 December [17]93., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
        The case will probably be heard in March and Mrs. [?] Turnbull's presence will not be material; the subjects which the testimony should point to are the fortune of Mr. [?] Turnbull, the injury done that of Mrs. Turnbull, and the expenses she has incurred since the separation; if he [Charles Lee] can learn that, he will prove himself useful in Alexandria.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia], to David Jones, Eastown, Chester County, [Pennsylvania], 17 January [17]94., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
        Note asking Jones to pay Garrett Cottringer $100; the bill is endorsed on the verso "Feby 11 1794 Reed Payment, Garrett Cottringer."
        Free Library of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
      - John Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [George Washington, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 31 August 1795., 1 page. Neg. and pos. Ph of ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
        Respectfully declines the Office of Attorney General of the U.S. because of his current business in Richmond.
        Original is located in the RG 59,
        National Archives, Washington, D.C.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia], to Charles Lee, Alexandria, [Virginia], [ca. December 1795]., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
        Has transmitted to the clerk of Dumfries a transverse to the Fauquier inquest; hopes that it will be determined by means of a demurrer at the next terms; discusses why he [John Marshall] wishes this.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 3 February [17]96., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
        Has just arrived safely in Philadelphia, and waits impatiently for the arrival of Mr. [Alexander] Campbell before considering a British debts case; his [John Marshall's] own case may not be taken up; mentions attending the theatre and compares Philadelphia's favorite actress, Mrs. Marshall, to Richmond's Mrs. [Anne West] Bignall; has not yet heard from his brother, James Markham Marshall; sends greetings to his children.
        Including Pst of ALS. 2 pages.
      - Richmond, Virginia Deed of land based on a 28 December 1794 contract between John Marshall and John McCreery, 24 June 1796., 4 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 1:3)
        In which he [John Marshall] sells 1,640 acres in Clarke County, Kentucky, near Strouds Station which had been patented to Marshall on 11 March 1784. At dollars per acre, McCreery pays Marshall £500 as a down payment, with the balance to be paid when full title is proved. The deed is recorded under the Seal of the General Court of Virginia on 15 June 1801.
      - Thomas Marshall, Buckpond, [Woodford County, Kentucky], to "Son" [John Marshall], Richmond, [Virginia], 9 September 1796., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
        Upset at the news of [Rawleigh] Colston's loss, and of the postponement of his [John Marshall's] visit to Buckpond, stating "the thoughts of seeing you once more...is a principle means of keeping me alive"; is pleased with his son's "part...in the present Storm"; would like to see his grandsons but fears the journey would tax their youthful constitutions; discusses his potential bequests of his property to the family; mentions he has paid taxes on his [John Marshall's] military land, but not on that which he gave to his grandson, Tom [Thomas Marshall] in Fayette [County, Kentucky]; thinks that "the political Horizon [is about] to clear up"; asks Marshall to notify Col. [Edward] Carrington that he [John Marshall] has sent Mr. [Peyton] Shorts' accounts to Mr. [Oliver] Walcot [sic] [Wolcott].
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Iredell, Edenton, North Carolina, 15 December [17]96., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
        Discusses Mr. [John] Eyre and [James] Nimmo, two of Virginia's electors in the presidential election of 1796; comments upon the distribution of Virginia's electoral votes between [Thomas] Jefferson, Sam[ue]l Adams, [?] Clinton, [Aaron] Burr, Gen[era]l [George] Washington, [?] Pin[c]kney, and John Adams; the Virginia Assembly displays its former hostility to Federalism; hopes North Carolina will not "tread the crooked path of Virginia"; will furnish [Alexander James] Dallas with his [John Marshall's] argument in the British debts case.
        Original is located in the Iredell Manuscripts,
        Duke University Library, Durham, North Carolina.
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1797., 17 items. (Box-folder 1:3-5)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Polly [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, [Virginia], 24 June 1797., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
          Tells of a day spent at Mount Vernon ("certainly one of the most delightful places in our country") on his way to Philadelphia via Alexandria; misses her so much as to send his man "Dick" to her with this letter; is treated well by his unkle [sic] [James] Keith in Alexandria; "I never was peremptory but I must now give you one positive order. It is be happy"; sends two letters which he accidentally carried off and asks her to send the one addressed to Genl. [Henry] Young to Mr. [John] Hopkins, and to send the other to his brother, [Thomas Marshall].
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to Caesar Rodney, Wilmington, Delaware, 31 June [sic] [17]97, [1 July 1797]., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
          Thanks him [Caesar Rodney] for informing him that some papers which had slipped out of his [John Marshall's] pocket were being held by Mr. McCullough at New Castle, whom he has requested to post them to Philadelphia.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 2 [sic] [3] July [17]97., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
          Discusses his voyage up the Chesapeake from Baltimore; mentions his first meeting with President John Adams; describes "heavy gloom" which hangs around the almost bankrupt Robert Morris and family; is impressed by the Vauxhall of Philadelphia and fashionable diversions; mentions estate of Mrs. [Susan] Heyward [sic] [Hayward] on the banks of the Schuylkil.